William Temple Franklin Papers 1775-1819 Mss.B.F86
American Philosophical Society
- William Temple Franklin Papers, 1775-1790; Mss.B.F86; 4.5 lin. feet
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 June 13; ALS, 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Gives news of his friends and what was done by the Notable Assembly; could not find Schrode's engraving of Prince of Brunswick, so sent another; wishes to know how much money would be needed to live in comfort in Philadelphia; regrets that Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson is not a member of the [Constitutional] Convention; introduces Mr. Saugrain.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 June 18; ALS, 1p.; Mason, Daniel. Newport
    Sends by Captain Lawton two packages with letter and receipt.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 June 19; ALS, 1p.; Bache, Richard
    Asks him to send his endorsement for about $3,000, as B[ache] and S[hee] are not in cash to pay off the whole of the last note, which ought to have been taken up yesterday.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 July 9; ALS, 2p.; le jeune, ---- Aury
    Sends the stockings; asks his help to collect a debt; encloses a letter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 July 31; A.L. 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Tells of the flight of M. [Charles Alexandre] de Calonne; gives the political situation in Paris; Passy is much changed; gives the account of the seizure of Mr. [Thomas] Paine's model of a bridge; wishes to hear the news of the [Constitutional] Convention in America; asks Dr. Franklin for the promised history.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 September 17; ALS, 1p.; Cork, George.
    Concerning the package sent by the Amboy stage boat.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 November 20; L. 3p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Learns from [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard that his portrait is copied from the original loaned by her. Refers to return of Chevalier de la Luzerne; thinks William Temple Franklin should be appointed Minister to France. Tells of her approaching confinement. The Brillon family in great consternation owing to the death of Mme. Paris, their oldest child. Recalls the time when Dr. Franklin called her his daughter and showed her so much affection.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 November 21; ALS, 1p.; Biddle, Charles
    Attended to the business but thought it best not to put his "name in nomination," as Mr. [Thomas] McKean said that Dr. Franklin appeared to wish that he be not run.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 December 4; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Has heard that Dr. Franklin is to be President of the new Congress; gives news of his various friends.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787 December 28; L. 3p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Has made arrangements that, in case of death or serious accident to her, the little green box (containing his portrait, etc.) will be handed over to M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard; the latter in very precarious health.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787; ALS, 4p.; Bache, Sarah
    Tells little items of news about Dr. Franklin, and of his desire to see him; visits of her children to the latter. Refers to the sailing of the "Alliance." Tells of Dr. Franklin's signing a marriage license or Mrs. Kepple, a rich widow.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1787; ALS, 1p.; Bache, William
    Will visit at the Park as soon as possible; has made a good invention or making silk lines and snoods.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 January 15; A.L. 2p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Sends friendly message from Mme. le B----. Learns from M. Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard that his health is not improving.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 February 3; ALS, 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Hopes that Congress has adopted the decisions of the [Constitutional] Convention; has bought and sent the glass for the electric machines; asks for information about certain business firms; the capitalists of the large towns are now occupied with American funds under the name of "Liquidated Debts." Gives news of various friends.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 March 1; Printed L.S. 1p.; Grand and Company
    Announcing change in firm and giving signatures.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 March 5; A.L. 4p.; Caillot, Blanchette
    Tells of the birth of her child [Armand] which almost cost her life. Gives news of Mme. Brillon's two married daughters.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 March 19; ALS, 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Wishes all information possible about America; his son is anxious to go there.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 March 20; ALS, 7p.; Grand and Co
    Gives statement of his affairs with the firm; thanks him for his trouble in the affair with Mr. [Thomas] Barclay; delighted that Dr. Franklin is in such good health; will send grain and books at first opportunity. Asks him to collect a debt from J. B. Ross. April 2. Thanks him for the plants for his garden, in return he will send books; Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson has gone to feel the pulse of the good Dutch.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 June 18; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Has sent several letters by Mr. Bourgoin who is waiting to deliver them in person, if it is possible to get them, he advises that this be done as quickly as possible; everything is in a great state of confusion.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 July 4; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Because of the expensiveness of the wine, he ordered half the quantity; he encloses the bill of lading.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 July 4; ALS, 4p.; Le Veillard fils, Louis
    Has had many business troubles and disappointments; would like to go to America; asks for information about the cost of living; expresses great devotion for him and his grandfather.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 August 6; A.L. 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    The political state is very uncertain; the States-General will be called in 1789.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1788 August 15; ALS, 1p.; Bondfield, John
    The Country is in a most upset state; "all the Provinces protest against the new measures as giving to the Court too great influence over the property of the people and taking away the sole barrier to check the Ministry." Sweden and Russia have begun to put in action a long smothered enmity.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1789 March 3; ALS, 1p.; Jay, John
    Enclosing the drafts.
  - to William Franklin (Mme. Lopez), 1789 April; ALS, 1p.; Drake, John
    Sends a medallion proof-print of their [Britannic] Majesties.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1790 January 25; ALS, 1p.; Coxe, William Jr.
    Notification of his election to the Burlington Society for the Pronotion of Agriculture and of Domestic Manufactures.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1790 July 16; ALS, 1p.; Jefferson, Thomas.
    Asking him to secure the refusal of the two houses, in Philadelphia, poken of. His object in taking two is to use the lower floor of oth for his public offices and the first floor and both gardens for his own use. Would like Mr. [Edmund] Randolph, the Attorney-General, or his neighbor.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 2p.; Arendt, Baron d'
    Concerning his intended payment of two bills which are about to fall due.
  - to William Temple Franklin, L.S. 1p.; d'Asp, L. O
    Will call and take dinner with him some day.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 2p.; Bache, Sarah
    Introducing Mr. [John] Lardner who is going to Paris on a visit; he has offered to take charge of some squirrel skins which she is sending to him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Baussan, Madame N
    Inviting him to dine with her.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Daer, Lord
    Regrets he had not his company at the race. Declines invitation to dine at
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Fribourg fils, -----
    Requesting payment of his bill for flowers, and sending a power of attorney from ----- Bates.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Fribourg fils, -----
    Quoting prices of costumes.
  - to William Temple Franklin, Wednesday; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Gambier, Miss
    Encloses a copy of the Unique, presented to her by Dr. Franklin; her high opinion of it. Will be out all day; puts her viol at his disposal.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.N. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Requesting him to return the letter from Martinique.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    The answer to his letter was unfavorable; asks that Dr. Franklin write certain papers for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Grand, Henry
    Sending Mr. Benjamin Vaughan's bill. Mr. Thomas Barclay's accounts.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1p.; Samuel Hannay's "Anti-venereal Specifick."
    Printed notice.
  - to William Temple Franklin, April 10; ALS, 1p.; Hoopes, A
    Asks him to tell what he knows about him to the bearer of the letter, who is the mother of a lad he is taking to America.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N.S. 1p.; Laneuville, Louis Pierre Panot Lombart, chevalier de, 1744-ca.1800
    Requests him to send, by bearer, a few bottles of Bordeaux wine.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Has delivered his challenge to ----- Leadwell who has accepted it.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Desires to see the "Craftsman" containing Mr. Braxton's letter.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asks him to lend him last Saturday's Mercury. Sends back the key of the garden door.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sending the remarks of Vaugelas and Père Bonhours.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Mme
    Sends the address of M. de Varseille[?].
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Maillart, -----
    Informing him that Denis Carcot has left for London.
  - to William Temple Franklin, Mem. 6p.; Medical Prescriptions
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Thanks him and his father for an invitation to dinner, but will have to postpone the pleasure until the following week.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Invites him to assist at a meeting of the French Academy.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 2p.; Morellet, abbé
    Sends memoir concerning certain persons, Cardinal de Rohan desiring to ascertain if they are known to Dr. Franklin and are deserving of the assistance they solicit.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 2p.; Morellet, abbé
    Has received Dr. Franklin's reply to Cardinal de Rohan's inquiry the latter has done all he can to have Darbelot [a former servant of Dr. Franklin] admitted to the Quinze-Vingt Asylum for the Blind.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Morellet, abbé
    Accepts his invitation and requests him to ask Mme. Brillon to loan them one of her pianos for the occasion.
  - to William Temple Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Morisan, -------
    Inviting him to be present at a meeting of a Society for giving balls, dances, etc.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; D'Oley, M.
    Fixing date for dinner at Neuilly.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Parker, John Jr.
    His father has decided not to go to Spa but to remain with him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Powers, Montfort
    Requesting him to postpone his invitation.
  - to William Temple Franklin, September 30; L. 1p.; Thomson, -----
    Inviting him to a family dinner.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    Telling of the virtues of castor oil and the mode of taking it.
  - to William Temple Franklin, 1780?; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wharton, ------ Jr.
    Returning books loaned by William Temple Franklin.
  - to William Temple Franklin, January 30; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wilfelsheim, -----
    Invitation to pass an evening at his house.
  - to William Temple Franklin, ALS, 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Inquires about Dr. Franklin's health; also about the affair of [Richmond] Springer and his comrades at Brest.
  - to William Temple Franklin, A.L. 1p.; Unidentified recipient
    Requesting him to return to the writer his letter for Chevalier de Chastellux, which he will deliver in person.
  - to William Temple Franklin, L. 2p.; Unidentified recipient
    Sends a memoir to be forwarded to London and translated into English.
  - to William Temple Franklin, L. 1p.; Unidentified recipient
    Writes on behalf of a wine grower who wishes to find a market for his wines in America; would send samples to [Richard] Bache and make arrangements with him.
  - to William Temple Franklin, L. 2p.; Unidentified recipient
    Asking information about Mlle. Andrillon who was employed as a child nurse by Mrs. [John] Jay, when the latter was living at Dr. Franklin's.
- William Temple Franklin Miscellaneous Collection, 1772-1819; Mss.B.F86x; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - Letter to Jonathan Williams, 1772 April 25; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Child's letter.
  - Letter to William T. Franklin, 1776 July 16; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, Elizabeth Downes
    Difficulties and sufferings since imprisonment of his dear father; mentions others made prisoners. Desires to be remembered to her father [Dr. Franklin] and Aunt Mecom.
  - Letter to [Sarah Franklin] Bache, 1780 March 18; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Bust being sent. Letters to father "might give suspicions." Squirrel skins for coat. B.F. requested cotton for a Lady. Mentions Mr. Brown, M. Gerard.
  - Letter to G[eorge] Fox, 1781 Jan. 15; ALS, 4p. 7 1/4" x 9"; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Americans in Paris; birth of the dauphin. Mentions his grandfather.
  - Letter to [George] Fox, 1781 Nov. 19; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    News of the war in America.
  - Letter to [Sarah Franklin Bache], 1782 Dec. 26; AL fragment, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Mentions R. Bache, furs and J. Vaughan. Fruit to B.F. Caustic comments on American Ladies in Paris: Mrs. Jay, Price, Izard, Ridly. Mentions his father. Lord Shelburne communicates with B.F.
  - Letter to M. Chardon, [1782 ?] Dec.; ALS, Franklin fils, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    In French. Introduces M. Putnam.
  - Letter to [John Jay?], 1784 May 16; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Forwards copy of resolve of Congress, pegging rate of U. S. dollars to the French livre Tournois.
    (see William TempleFranklin papers.)
  - Letter to [Thomas] Ruston, 1785 May 2; ALS, 2p. mutilated; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Sends letter to be forwarded to his father [William Franklin], and a parcel containing contraband goods for Dr. Bancroft.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Purchased from the American Autograph Shop, April 1939, $33.
    FILM54-57 FRAME130
  - Letter to [Donatien] Le Ray de Chaumont, 1785 July 16; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Arrival of M. de Chaumont's son in America; B. Franklin's arrival in Rouen; Abbé Morellet's desire to possess a certain tapestry armchair once used by Franklin. In French.
    Purchased from George W. Dalton, November 1938, $75.
  - Letter to T[homas] Jefferson, 1785 July 20; Photo. of ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    His grandfather stood journey to Havre well; arrangements made with Capt. Truxton. Investigation of box containing papers and books. Arrival of M. Houdon.
    Presented by C.F. Jenkins,1948.
  - Contract with William Pyne for managing a farm in New Jersey, 1786 Feb. 25; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    FILM 54-family FRAME 39
  - Lease to Solomon Ridgway, 1787 March 25; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    FILM54-family FRAME 40
  - Lease to John Howell, 1788 March 8; The signatures have been blotted out.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    FILM 54-family FRAM 41
  - DS to William Temple Franklin, 1788 March 15; Ridgway, Solomon
    Objections to contract on managing farm.
    FILM 54-Family FRAME 42
  - ALS Cy, 4p, 1788 March 23; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    FILM 54-family FRAME 43
  - Sketch of William Temple Franklin's services on the United States of America; Passy, 1789 May 23; Photostat 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to George Washington, 1790 Oct.13; Photostat of ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Plans to go to England and France; offers services to Washington. Purpose in going is to derive advantage from the publication of his grandfather's Works, and not because of disgust and disappointment in not receiving governmental appointment. His loyalty to America, its laws and its Chief Magistrate.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    Original: General records of the Dept. of State, Miscellaneous letters. RG 59. National Archives. Presented by Philip M. Hamer, July 1953.
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1790 Oct. 25; Photostat, 1p.; Washington, George,pres.U.S.,1732-1799
    Presented by P.M. Hamer, July 1953.
    Original: General records of the Dept. of State, Miscellaneous letters. RG 59 National Archives.
    Printed: Fitzpatrick, 31,134.
  - Letter to Henry Drinker, 1790 Nov. 1; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Acknowledges sample of maple sugar.
    Purchased from F. G. Sweet, Sept. 15, 1939,$15.
    FILM 54-57 FRAME 131
  - List of books for Benjamin Franklin Bache, [1790]; Photo. of A.D. 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    From original in possession of Library Company of Philadelphia. Presented by Edwin Wolf, II; Nov.1962.
  - Letter to unidentified recipient, [ca. 1790]; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Asks that the 91 volumes of the Histoire de l'Academie bequeathed by his grandfather to the Philosophical society be sent for.
    Presented by Mr. Frederic R. Kirkland, January 1950.
  - Letter to [William Template] Franklin, 1792 Jan. 29; Photostat, 4p.; Feuillet, Laurent Francis?, 1768-1843.
    In French. Relates to a French edition of his grandfather's works.
    From original in Library of Congress.
  - Power of attorney to George Fox to receive interest on stocks, 1793 Feb. 11; A.D.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to Henry Drinker, 1794 March 12; Photocopy of ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Sale of land in Pennsylvania. Business.
    From original in Friends Archives, Phila. Henry Drinker correspondence, I. Copy courtesy W. Spawn, 1/27/70.
  - Description of land for sale in Pennsylvania refers interested persons to W. T. Franklin, 1794 Sept. 12; Photocopy of D, 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823, Drinker, Henry?, 1734-1809
  - Letter to Henry Drinker, 1794 Sept. 12; Photocopy of ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Possible sale of Pennsylvania lands.
  - Certificate, no.968, issued to William Temple Franklin for five shares of stock; Phila, 1795 April 18; Photostat, 1p.; North American land company (Oversize 1)
  - Certificate, No.1260, for one share of stock issued to William Temple Franklin; Philadelphia, 1795 April 18; 1p.; North American land company
    Presented by James Lewis Hook, April 1955.
  - Certificate for ten shares of stock issued to William Temple Franklin; Philadelphia, 1795 April 18; 1p.; North American land company
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] LeRoy, 1795 May 14; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Introduces William Bache and asks that he be introduced to friends of B. Franklin.
  - Letter to Fulmar Skipwith, 1795 June 23; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    With this came reproduction of medallion of William Temple Franklin.
  - Letter to John Nicholson, 1795 Aug. 13; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Bill of sale to Thomas and Nathaniel Jefferys for 15 shares of stock of the Bank of the U.S, 1795 Oct. 6; Pr.DS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Certificate stating that Pierre Deschamps is his servant, and requesting a passport for him, 1796 July 27; A.D.S. 2p. D.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Contains a note signed, Corsange, dated 11. Thermidor An 4, certifying to the authenticity of William Temple Franklin's signature, and a similar note certifying to the authenticity of Corsange's signature.
    Purchased from F.G. Sweet, March 3, 1939.
  - Letter to Jonathan Russel, 1811 June 20; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Will and letters of administration, 1814 Oct. 24-1825; Photocopies, 29p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to J. W. Francis, 1816 June 12; Photostat of ALS, 3p. and enc., 3p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Pertains to the publication of his edition of the [Benjamin] Franklin manuscripts. Information for Mr. Duane.
    Presented by I.B. Cohen.
  - Letter to James Monroe, 1816 Dec. 18.; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Sends volume of the Private correspondence of Dr. Franklin.
  - Letter to Georges Adrien Crapelet, 1819 Sept. 15; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    In French. Introduces [Henry?] Colburn.
  - Observations on the French Language, D. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    In hand of W. T. Franklin(?)